Guide to the D. H. (David Herbert) Lawrence Collection, 1913-1973
Department of Special Collections
- [Cecil] Gray. Zennor, St. Ives, Cornwall, n.d., Thursday [? 14 June 1917]. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Cecil Gray. Tregerthen, [Cornwall], Wed[nesday], 11 July 1917., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 30)
- [Cecil] Gray. Treterthen, [Cornwall], n.d., Monday [? 27 August 1917]. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- [Cecil Gray]. Zennor, St. Ives, Cornwall, 12 October 1917. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Grigio [Cecil Gray]. 32 Well Walk, Hampstead, [London] N.W. Wed[nesday], 17 October 1917. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Cecil Gray. Hampstead, [London, N.W.] Friday, [19 October 1917]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Cecil Gray. 44 Mecklenburgh Sq. [London] W.C., n.d., Thesday, [23 October 1917]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 35)
- [Cecil Gray?]. 44 Mecklenburgh Square, [London] W.C. 1, n.d., Monday [? 29 October 1917]. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Cecil Gray. 44 Mecklenburgh [Sq. London], Friday, 2 November 1917., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 37)
- [Cecil Gray]. 44 Mecklenburgh Square [London] W.C. 1, n.d. [?7 November 1917]. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Cecil Gray. 44 Mecklenburgh [Sq., London], Friday, [9 November 1917]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 39)
- [Cecil Gray]. 44 Mecklenburgh Square [London] W.C. 1, n.d., Tuesday, [? 4 December 1917]. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- [Cecil Gray?]. Hermitage, Newbury, [Berkshire], n.d., [? January 1918]. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- [Cecil Gray]. Hermitage, [nr. Newbury, Berkshire], n.d., Sunday, [? 20 January 1918]. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- [Cecil] Gray. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks]hire], n.d., Thursday, [? 7 February 1918]. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- [Cecil Gray]. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks[hire], 12 March 1918. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Grigio [Cecil Gray]. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks[hire], 18 April 1918. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Grigio [Cecil Gray]. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks[hire], 19 April 1918. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- [Cecil Gray?]. Mountain Cottage, Midaleton by Wirksworth, Derby[shire], 3 July 1918. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Grigio [Cecil Gray]. Mountain Cottage, Middleton by Wirksworth, Derby[shire], 22 July 1918. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- [J.B.] Pinker. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks[hire], 18 June 1919. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Mrs. Helen Thomas. Chapel Farm Cottage, Hermitage, nr. Newbury, Berks[hire], 9 July 1919. (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Mrs. [Douglas] Goldring. c/o Mrs. Carswell, Holly Bush House, Holly Mount, Hampstead, [Lonodn] N.W. 3, 14 October 1919., (Post cardO). (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Douglas Goldring. Hampstead, [London] Wed[nesday] night, 15 October 1919., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Douglas Goldring. 5 Acacia Rd. Hampstead, [London] N.W. 8, Wed[nesday], 5 November 1919., (Post card). (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Douglas Goldring. 5 Acacia Rd. [Hampstead, London] N.W. 8, Thursday, 13 November 1919., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 54)
- [John] Cournos. Villa Mirenda, Scandicci, Florence, Italy, 8 May 1926. (Box 1, Folder 55)
- [Maria Christina] Chambers. Villa Mirenda, Scandicci, Florence, Italy, 11 November 1927. (Box 1, Folder 56)
- [Charles] Wilson. Villa Mirenda, Scandicci, Florence, 5 December 1927. (Box 1, Folder 57)
- [Charles] Wilson. Villa Mirenda, Scandicci, Florence, 23 December 1927. (Box 1, Folder 58)
- [Maria Cristina] Chambers. Chalet Beau Site, Les Diablerets, Suisse (Vaud.), 18 Fevrier 1928. (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Arabella [Dorothy Yorke]. Kesselmatte, Gsteig b. Gstaad, (Bern), Switzerland, 4 August 1928. (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Arabella [Dorothy Yorke]. Kesselmatte, [Gsteig b. Gstaad, Switzerland], Friday [17 August 1928]. (Box 1, Folder 61)
- [Maria Cristina] Chambers. Kesselmatte, Gsteig b. Gstaad, [Switzerland], 25 August 1928. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- [Maria Cristina] Chambers. [Kesselmatte, Gsteig b. Gstaad, Bern], Switzerland, 11 September 1928. (Box 1, Folder 63)
- [Maria Cristina] Chambers. Baden Saden [Germany, 26 September 1928. (Box 1, Folder 64)
- [Maria Cristina] Chambers. Bandol, Var, France, 28 December 1928. (Box 1, Folder 65)
- [P.R.] Stephensen. Hotel Principe Alfonso, Palma de Mallorca, Spain, Sat[urday], 18 May [1929]. (Box 1, Folder 66)
- [Maria Cristina Chambers]. N.p., n.d. [Late June, 1929]., (A signed note.) (Box 1, Folder 67)
- A note to Lawrence from Maria Cristina and his answer. N.p., n.d.[Forte dei Marmi, Italy. Late June 1929.], (Not signed.) (Box 1, Folder 68)
- [Maria Cristina Chambers]. Pensione Giuliani, Forte dei Marmi, [Italy. ? 6 July 1929]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Maria Cristina Chambers. Flrenze, Wed[nesday, 10 July 1929]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. Firenze, n.d. [?14 July 1929]. (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Maria Cristina Chambers. Baden Baden [Germany], Friday, [19 July 1929]., (Post card.) (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. Ludwig-Wilhelmstift, Baden Baden, Germany, 22 July 1929. (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. c/o Sig. G. Orioli, 6 Lungarno Corsini, Forlence, Italy, 23 August 1929. (Box 1, Folder 74)
- [John] Cournos. Rottach-[am-Tegernsee, Germany], 14 September [1929]. (Box 1, Folder 75)
- [Charles] Lahr. Rottach-[am-Tegernsee, Germany], n.d., Saturday, [? 14 September 1929]. (Box 1, Folder 76)
- [Maria Cristina Chambers]. N.p., n.d. [Fall, 1929].(Note -- not signed.) (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Notations principally about publishers to [Maria Cristina Chambers]. N.p., n.d. [Fall, 1929].(Not signed). (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. Villa Veau-Soleil, Bandol, Var, France, 28 September 1929. (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. Villa Beau-Soleil, Bandol, Var, France, 11 October 1929. (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Maria Cristina [Chambers]. Villa Beau-Soleil, Bandol, Var, France, 25 October 1929. (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Transcripts of D.H. Lawrence correspondence (Box 1, Folder 82)
- 9 holograph poems signed by D.H. Lawrence. The Mowers; Green; All of Roses; Fireflies in the Corn; A Woman and Her Dead Husband; The Wind; The Rascal; Illicit; Birthday; The Mother of Sons. Purchased 1947., 9 leaves consecutively written on tablet paper. (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Holograph poem, unsigned. No title., 1 leaf.
    1st line: Reach over, then, reach over across the chasm in the dark. Gift of Albert M. Bender, 1940.
  - Holograph poem, unsigned. no title., 1 leaf
    1st line: Traitors, oh liars, you Judas lot
    On verso another[?] poem, list line: Are you pining to be superior? Gift of Albert M. Bender, 1940.
  - Holograph manuscript of the poem Guards! A Review in Hyde Park 1913. In two parts: The Crowd Watches and Evolutions of Soldiers. D. H. Lawrence From Bay C. W. Berd. Source unknown. One typescript of the same., 1 leaf.
    All of the above D.H. Lawrence correspondence has been microfilmed.
  - Original typescript of Do Women Change?, with corrections made in ink by D.H. Lawrence. Gift of [Mr. and Mrs. Harley R. Carter?]., 7 leaves.
  - Holograph manuscript of the forward to Women in Love. Hermitage, 12 Sept. 1919.(This forward was suppressed before publication.) Purchased, 1935., 1 leaf.
    This item is missing
  - Photograph of D.H. Lawrence painting: Resurrection.
  - Trial and proof pages of first and second editions of Lady Chatterley's Lover.
- Original typescript of Young Lorenzo by Ada Lawrence and G. Stuart Gelder with corrections made in ink. Purchased, 1954., 173 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 84)
  Published by G. Orioli, Florence, Italy [1931]).
- Original manuscript of The Thimble, 24 pages (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Typescripts of letter to Miss Chambers and Mr. Pinker. (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Original typescript of The Phoenix: His Life a Burning. By Mark Schorer, Oct. 30, 1908.Lecture at Lawrence Exhibit in Bender Room. (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Negative of D.H. Lawrence letter written Dec. 15, 1921to Lady Ottoline Morrell. (Box 2, Folder 88)
  Presentation slip from Frieda Lawrence to Mrs. Gordon Crotch. (found in copy of Lady Chatterley's Lover.)
- Addition: 1978
  - Crayon portrait of D.H. Lawrence in colors on grey paper measuring 13 3/8 x 8 3/8, actual portrait 8 1/2 x 5 3/8 inches. (Box 2, Folder 89)
    Purchase from Seven Gables, NLC602, FJS, Jan 9 78. See reference file on more information.
  - 1. 1913 Sep 4,D.H. Lawrence, Irschenhausen, Bavaria, to Henry Savage, London, with ANS by Frieda von Richthofen, ...my whole working philosophy is that the only stable happiness for mankind is that it shall live married in blessed union to woman-kind... Frieda's ANS: Savage's writing style. With envelope, With envelope, 1913, Sep 5., ALS, 2 1/2 pp. (3); 2 pp. (2).; (2). (Box 2, Folder 90.)
  - 2. n.d.Frieda von Richthofen to Henry Savage, n.p. Richard Middleton, his suicide and relation to women. ...women should be satisfied to be and let the men do. We can do so much more that way. Lawrence, J.J. Rousseau. (c. Oct 1913), ALS, 4 pp (4).
  - 3. 1914 May 7D.H. Lawrence, Lerici, Italy, to Henry Savage, London, with ANS by Frieda von Richthofen, With envelope, 1914 May 8.Lawrence and Frieda's imminent marriage. Condolences re Savage's mother's death. Imploring Savage to give up the Raynes Park literary milieu and writing. I think you ought to remain among books, but rather as a soldier of literature than a writer. Discusses Women in love, feelings for England. Frieda's ANS: death and Lawrence., ALS, 5 pp (3); 1 p (1).
  - 1973 Sep 29.Erica Jong, N.Y. to Leo, np. D.H. Lawrence, ...the women's movement condemnation of him is rediculous. Birds, beasts, and flowers and Phoenix., TLS (Box 2, Folder 91.)